danny.carbonero@gmail.com dannycarbonero.github.io

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

I enjoy solving challenging biological and mathematical problems by crafting machine learning solutions backed by the implantation of massive data sets. My current research involves developing novel, and adapting existing, machine learning methods for analysis of large neuroscientific data sets to better understand the brain.

#### **EDUCATION**

## PhD Biomedical Engineering, Boston University

2019 - Present

Dissertation: "Machine Learning Framework for Analyzing State-Dependent Neuronal Network Dynamics in Calcium Recordings"

Advisors: John A. White, PhD & Mark A. Kramer, PhD

MS Biomedical Engineering, Boston University

2019 - 2022

BS Biomedical Engineering, University of Miami

2015 - 2019

GPA: 3.8/4.0, Cum Laude

## PROFESSIONAL AND RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## Graduate Research Fellow

March 2020-present

Neuronal Dynamics Laboratory (NDL), Department of Biomedical Engineering, Boston University Advisor: John White, PhD

- Develop and adapt linear and non-linear dimensionality reduction (DR) machine learning methods for unsupervised neuronal network analyses recorded with calcium imaging under unique neural contexts.
- Built constraining for non-negative matrix factorization DR to allow for semi-supervised analytical approaches to neuronal network dynamics.
- Develop and write software wrapper packages to make complex machine learning methods more easily accessible and implementable to end users.
- Collaborate with experimental lab scientists to iteratively adapt and apply developed methods to their collected data to answer groundbreaking, novel, and complex neurological questions.
- Design analysis pipeline for rigorously characterizing neuronal network dynamics under: increasing concentrations of anesthetic sedation, natural and artificial memory recall.

Breakout Fellow March 2023 – Present

**Breakout Ventures** 

- Develop investment acumen and proficiency in navigating the venture capital landscape with Breakout investment team through case studies.
- Evaluate specific technologies and their comparative scientific and commercial viabilities with respect to other technologies and the greater Biotech landscape.
- Serve as strategic partner in Biotech hub of Boston, Massachusetts, evaluating emerging technologies, startups, and entrepreneurs to connect promising ventures with Breakout's expertise, resources, and funding.

Associate Engineer May 2019 – August 2019

Bio-Vitro Inc, Supervisor: Siddarth Rawal, MD

- Optimized design of previously constructed fluid handling platform for unattended, automated, cell culture and cell signaling analysis under physiological conditions.
- Design was produced and sent to collaborating labs to make organs-on-chips more technically accessible.

danny.carbonero@gmail.com dannycarbonero.github.io

#### **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

May 2018-August 2018

Research Experience for Undergraduates – Neurological Prosthesis Research Laboratory, Department of Biomedical Engineering, Duke University, Advisor: Warren Grill, PhD

- Modified and completely automated a fully computational, Deep Brain Stimulation, Parkinson's Disease (PD) Neurological model to simulate networks of neurons using experimentally recorded data as inputs.
- Modeled PD in rat brain using upstream, experimentally recorded, neuron firing as input to simulate, characterize, and analyze downstream Thalamus function and activity to assess effectiveness of Deep Brian Stimulation as treatment for PD.

#### **Undergraduate Research Assistant**

May 2017 – May 2019

Physiomimetic Microsystems Laboratory (PML), Department of Biomedical Engineering, University of Miami Advisor: Ashutosh Agarwal, PhD

- Developed automated software pipelines for immunohistochemical fluorescent microscope image data acquisition, processing, and analysis for reproducible quantification of organ-on-chip systems.
- Wrote front-end software packages to allow end users to easily and reproducibly process and analyze image data for various platforms (heart, neuro-muscular junction, metastasis).
- Designed, prototyped, and manufactured an integrated and completely automated platform for continuous cell culture and dynamic cell secretion analysis of these organ-on-chip systems.

Student Analyst January 2017 – May 2017

Department of Continuing International Education, University of Miami, Supervisor: Magaly Abreu

- Developed early iteration of real-time, self-updating student database to consolidate information and ease access.
- Created financial reports to clearly and intuitively visualize large volumes of financial information.

## **AWARDS/HONORS**

F31 Ruth L. Kirschstein Predoctoral Individual National Research Service Award	2023
NSF Research Traineeship Program Understanding the Brain: Neurophotonics Trainee	2020
NIH Translational Research in Biomaterials Grant Funded Trainee	2019
Boston University Biomedical Engineering Distinguished Fellowship	2019
University of Miami College of Engineering Senior Design Industry Impact Award	2019
Alpha Eta Mu Beta - National biomedical engineering honor society	2019
Omicron Delta Kappa Honor Society - National leadership honor society	2019
Tau Beta Pi Honor Society -National engineering honor society	2018
University of Miami President's Scholarship	2015

#### SKILLS

Machine Learning and Data Science: Linear Dimensionality Reduction, Matrix Decomposition, Manifold Learning,

Clustering, Unsupervised/Semi-Supervised/Supervised Learning, Deep Learning (Artificial Neural-Networks)

Time Series Analysis, Image Analysis

Data Science Software: Scikit-Learn, Scipy, Statsmodels, Pandas, Tensorflow, Numba

Programming: Highly Proficient in: Python, MATLAB

Comfortable with: HTML, CSS, R Familiar with: C, C++, Java

High Performance Computing: Unix, Linux, Remote Super Computing Clusters, Code Parallelization (Python, MATLAB),

GPU Computing, git Version Control

**Engineering Design:** CAD, SOLIDWORKS, Rapid Prototyping **Software:** Arduino IDE, COMSOL Multiphysics, ImageJ

Document Preparation and Graphic Desing: Microsoft Office, Adobe Illustrator, Figma

**Certifications:** Six Sigma Green Belt

Languages: Native in Spanish, fluent in English

danny.carbonero@gmail.com dannycarbonero.github.io

### LEADERSHIP & MENTORING

### **Nucleate, Boston Chapter**

#### **Director of Communications**

June 2023 – Present

- Direct all Communications and manage the Communications team of the Boston chapter of Nucleate, a student-led organization aiming to facilitate venture creation of pioneering life sciences companies.
- Write all promotional and professional materials advertising to the community at large or disseminating information to the rest of Nucleate leadership and participating venture teams.
- Collaborate with other directors to set communication weekly plan and agenda.

#### **Vice President of Communications**

**November 2022 - May 2023** 

- Built automated email pipelines to ensure both chapter leadership, and venture teams were updated on all organizational information.
- Worked with the communications team, and leaders of other teams, to write and publish weekly newsletter.

## **Boston University Biotech Group**

Founder

January 2023 - Present

- One of three founders of the Boston University Biotech Group (BUBG), aiming to bridge the gap between BU graduate students and the greater industrial Boston biotech community.
- Working with university directors to further develop and implement programs to ease, teach, and encourage graduate student founding of commercially viable biotech companies.
- Developing several "pitching" programs to teach scientific ideation and communication.
- Plan and continue to carry out biotech speaker series (venture capital investors, start-up founders, biotech reporters) to engage and expose students to alternative career paths and opportunities.

### Neuronal Dynamics Lab - 2021-2022 Senior Design Team Advisor

**August 2021 – May 2022** 

• Advised and mentored senior design team through development of random forest and support vector machine (SVM) depth of anesthesia classifiers using standard neural recordings.

### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- **D Carbonero**, J Noueihed, MA Kramer, JA White, "Non-Negative Matrix Factorization for Analyzing Neuronal Network Dynamics in Calcium Recordings" (in preparation)
- J Noueihed, **D Carbonero**, FR Fernandez, JA White, "Balance of Excitation and Inhibition in the Primary Somatosensory Cortex Layer 2/3 Under Isoflurane Anesthesia" (in preparation)
- J Noueihed, **D Carbonero**, FR Fernandez, JA White, "Multisession Processing of Multiphoton Calcium Imaging" (under review)
- RR Besser, A Alassaf, **D Carbonero**, I Ortiz, R Maciel, M Saporta, A Agarwal, "A Compartmentalized Platform for In-Vitro Assembly of Neuromuscular Junctions and the Implications for Studying Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease Type 2E" (under review)
- RR Besser, A C Bowles, A Alassaf, **D Carbonero**, R Maciel, M Saporta, A Agarwal, "A Chemically Defined Media for Culture of C2C12 Skeletal Muscle and Human Induced Pluripotent Stem Cell Derived Spinal Spheroids" <u>Cellular and Molecular Bioengineering</u>
- RR Besser, R Maciel, **D Cabonero**, A Alassaf, I Claure, E Jones, J Reda, A Bowles, W Bachelor, N Ziebarth, R Rodriquez, A Khan, M Saporta, A Agarwal: "Enzymatically Crosslinked Gelatin-Laminin Hydrogels for Applications in Neuromuscular Tissue Engineering", *Biomaterials Science*, 8(2), 591-606 HIGHLIGHTED AS COVER ARTICLE
- A Alassaf, G Tansik, V Mayo, L Wubker, **D Carbonero**, A Agarwal: "Engineering Anisotropic Cardiac Monolayers on Microelectrode Arrays for Non-invasive Analyses of Electrophysiological Properties" *Analyst*, 145(1), 139-140 included in themed collection on bioanalytical tools for enabling precision medicine
- M Ishahak, L Birman, **D Carbonero**, J Hill, A Hernandez, S Rawal, A Agarwal: "Integrated platform for operating and interrogating organs-on-chips", *Analytical Methods*, 11(43), 5645-5651 *highlighted in the Emerging Investigator Series*

danny.carbonero@gmail.com dannycarbonero.github.io

RR Besser, M Ishahak, V Mayo, **D Carbonero**, I Claure, A Agarwal: "Engineered Microenvironments for Maturation of Stem Cell Derived Cardiac Myocytes", *Theranostics*, 8(1), 124-140

### **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- **D Carbonero**, J Noueihed, MA Kramer, JA White, "Linear Dimensionality Reduction for Neuronal Network Analysis Under Isoflurane Sedation in Mice", Society for Neuroscientists 2022 Annual Meeting, San Diego CA, November 2022
- **D Carbonero**, J Noueihed, MA Kramer, JA White, "Linear Dimensionality Reduction for Analyzing Calcium Recordings", Biomedical Engineering Society 2022 Annual Meeting, San Antonio TX, October 2022 (**Platform Oral Presentation**)
- **D Carbonero**, J Noueihed, JA White, "Principal Component Analysis for Neuronal Network Analysis Under Isoflurane Sedation in Mice", Society for Neuroscientists 2021 Annual Meeting, November 2021
- **D Carbonero**, J Noueihed, JA White, "Principal Component Analysis for Neuronal Network Analysis Under Isoflurane Sedation in Mice", Biomedical Engineering Society 2021Annual Meeting, Orlando FL, October 2021
- R Besser, R Maciel, A Alassaf, **D Carbonero**, M Saporta, A Agarwal, "In Vitro Recapitulation of The Dysfunctional Neuromuscular Junction In Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease", TERMIS 2019 Annual Conference & Exhibition, Orlando FL. December 2019
- R Besser, **D Carbonero**, I Claure, A Alassaf, A Bowles, E Jones, J Reda, W Bachelor, R Rodriquez, A Khan, R Maciel, M Saporta, A Agarwal, "Enzymatically Crosslinked Gelatin-Laminin Hydrogels for Disease on Chip Applications", Society for Biomaterials 2019 Annual Meeting, Seattle WA, April 2019
- **D Carbonero**, K Kumaravelu, W M Grill, "Computational Analysis of Neural Activity Recorded during Subthalamic Nucleus Deep Brain Stimulation in a Rat Model of Parkinson's Disease", Biomedical Engineering Society 2018 Annual Meeting, Atlanta GA, October 2018
- R Besser, R Maciel, A Alassaf, **D Carbonero**, M Dvornik, I Claure, M Saporta, A Agarwal, "In Vitro Recapitulation of the dysfunctional neuromuscular junction in Charcot-Mari-Tooth disease", Biomedical Engineering Society 2018 Annual Meeting, Atlanta GA, October 2018
- M Ishahak, L Alamda-Sabate, **D Carbonero**, S Rawal, A Agarwal, "Organ-on-Chip Platform with Integrated, Non-Invasive Oxygen Monitoring", Pittcon 2018, Orlando FL., February 2018.
- **D Carbonero**, R Besser, A Agarwal, "TwitchRead: Analyzing Contraction in Engineered Skeletal Muscle Tissue Co-Cultured with Neurospheres", Biomedical Engineering Society 2017 Annual Meeting, Phoenix AZ., October 2017

## INVITED TALKS

Boston University Stochastic Processes in Neuroscience Seminar Series

Boston MA, December 2022

Principal Component Analysis as a Change of Basis for Neural Signals

• Seminar series to discuss physical feasibility of stochastic models for neuroscientific data analysis.

# **Boston University Neurophotonics Center Tech Talk Tutorial Series**

Boston MA, September 2022

**Linear Dimensionality Reduction for Analyzing Calcium Recordings (a toolbox)** 

• Seminar series to spread awareness on technologies under development to foster collaboration between labs.

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

### **Graduate Teaching Fellow**

September 2021- December 2021

EK 381 – Probability, Statistics and Data Science for Engineers Department of Mechanical Engineering, Boston University

## **Graduate Teaching Fellow**

September 2020- December 2020

EK 125 – Introduction to Programming for Engineers Department of Mechanical Engineering, Boston University